Welcome, this is my first time I'm talking at FOSDEM.
You can follow along the slides via the link.
By the time this airs I hope to be able to provide subtitles for download.
The content will be close to speaker notes you can find either on the right hand
or at the bottom, depending on your screen.
My name is André Jaenisch.
I'm currently working as Software Engineer at Jambit.
It's a medium-sized software provider from Germany.
This talk has nothing to do with my work.
Since this reveal.js presentation is pre-recorded using OBS Studio
please ask your questions at the end.
In between you'll find scenes taken with ScreenCam on Android.
I'd welcome if you'd allow me to
add your comments to the presentation slides afterwards
Please tell me, if you want to opt-in.
Unless otherwise noted, the content is made available under
the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license.
Let's start with Responsive Web Design!
I'm quite sure you ran into this picture in some form before.
It's a typical marketing image to depict a web app
that's usable on different devices by adjusting the layout accordingly.
… but …
What if I told you that this approach could fell short?
How would you classify this Samsung Galaxy Note 3 with a pen?
Is it a mobile?
It's small enough to get counted as one.
But you have a pointer device - the pen.
… so …
… designing for it like for a desktop?
You'd waste real screen estate otherwise after all.
While I was preparing for a Game Jam in early 2020 …
I ran across an article on Mozilla Developer Network
regarding Sensor APIs.
I was aware of the ability to recognise motion
and orientation
from my days with Firefox OS
but by now, there are more Sensor APIs available.
This talk will show you some tech demos.
They're not ready for production usage yet in general.
Since normally you'll need to toggle a flag in the browser to get access to the underlying API.
But that shouldn't stop you to show off what's possible on the web!
My first demo is called „What's the user doing?”
It's a showcase I run into years ago.
It highlights the impact on privacy sensor data can have.
You can see I can tell whether
the user is sitting, walking, taking a picture.
I was even able to test like I lay down the phone on the desk.
This is normally not data you want to hand out without second thought.
After my Game Jam I decided to create a small demo site
which runs some primitive checks on your device capabilities.
Note, that some of this is done with CSS and some of it is with JavaScript.
so you have Media Query for example for the hover,
for detecting Pointer Devices, Aspect ratios
Colours, orientation.
I'm not sure what colours is meant to do
but I can think of use cases for example for e-book readers.
Since I created the page I started to design tooltips based on
the hover Media Query instead of guessing from the screen size.
Orientation could be used if you have certain criteria.
For example, you have a sidebar which is needed and the thing you want to show is next to it.
Device Motion is the movement of a device in the room.
Orientation is how you hold it.
Accelerometer measures the velocity.
Ambient Light Level measures the relative light around the device.
I have a small demo for it.
Web Bluetooth is available on Chrome
but also only behind a flag.
I've got something prepared for that for you.
Geolocation should be known from for example map apps.
Gyroscope is a compass so to speak.